<section id="Axes">
<title>Axes</title>

<para>
A Multigraph graph has one or more horizontal axes, and one or more
vertical axes.  The location and other display properties of the axes
are specified with the <sgmltag>horizontalaxis</sgmltag> and
<sgmltag>verticalaxis</sgmltag> elements in the &mugl; file.
This includes mathematical information such as the data type
and range of values along the axis, as well as display information such
as how the axis should be labeled, a title to be drawn for the axis, and
so on.
</para>

<para>
A &mugl; file can contain any number (0 or more)  of <sgmltag>horizontalaxis</sgmltag>
and <sgmltag>verticalaxis</sgmltag>
elements.  Each graph always contains at least one horizontal axis and
at least one vertical axis.
If the <sgmltag>horizontalaxis</sgmltag> element is missing,
multigraph creates a horizontal axis with all the default settings.
The same is true for the the <sgmltag>verticalaxis</sgmltag> tag.
</para>

<para>
The <sgmltag>horizontalaxis</sgmltag> and
<sgmltag>verticalaxis</sgmltag> elements have the following
attributes:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>id</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
An identifier that can be used to refer to this axis elsewhere in the
&mugl; file.  If this attribute is missing, it defaults to "x"
for the first horizontal axis, and to "x1", "x2", ... for any additional
horizontal axes.  The default is "y" for the first
vertical axis, and "y1", "y2", ... for any additional vertical axes.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>type</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Indicates the data type for the axis.  Should be one of "number" or "datetime".  The default
is "number".
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>position</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Indicates where this axis should be drawn, as an offset, in pixels,
from the left edge (for vertical axes) or bottom edge (for
horizontal axes) of the plot area.  The default is 0.  Note that this
offset is relative to the plotarea, not the padding box, so the default
axis positions are long the left and bottom edges of the plotarea.  Negative
offsets move the axes away from the plotarea and into the padding box.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>positionbase</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Normally the <sgmltag>position</sgmltag> attribute indicates the position
of an axis with respect to the left (for vertical axes) or bottom (for horizontal axes)
edge of the plot area. The <sgmltag>positionbase</sgmltag> attribute can be used
to change this interpretation so that the <sgmltag>position</sgmltag> value
is relative to the right or top edge instead.  Its value should be either
'left', 'right', 'bottom', or 'top'.  The default for <sgmltag>positionbase</sgmltag> is
'left' for vertical axes and 'bottom' for horizontal axes.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>pregap</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
For horizontal axes: a gap size in pixels between the left edge of the plotarea
area and the left endpoint of the axis.  For vertical axes: a gap size in pixels
between the bottom edge of the plotarea and the bottom endpoint of the axis.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>postgap</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
For horizontal axes: a gap size in pixels between the right edge of the plotarea
and the right endpoint of the axis.  For vertical axes: a gap size in pixels
between the top edge of the plotarea and the top endpoint of the axis.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>min</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
The minimum data value for the axis --- i.e., the data value corresponding to the
left (for horizontal axes) or bottom (for vertical axes) endpoint of the axis.
If the axis is a "number" type axis, this value is a number.  If it is a "datetime" type
axis, the value is a datetime in the format YYYYMMDDHHmmss.
</para>
<para>
Alternatively "min" value may be the keyword "auto", which indicates that the minimum
data value for the axis should be computed from the given data.  This only works
for data sources where the entire data set is available at the outset --- it does not
work for web-service based data sources.
</para>
<para>
The default value for the "min" attribute is "auto".
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>minoffset</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
A number which determines the point on the axis that will be associated with the
<sgmltag>min</sgmltag> value. <sgmltag>minoffset</sgmltag> defaults to 0, which means
that the <sgmltag>min</sgmltag> value is associated with the left or bottom endpoint
of the axis.  If <sgmltag>minoffset</sgmltag> is not 0, then the <sgmltag>min</sgmltag>
will be associated with a point on the axis that is that many pixels away from
the left or bottom endpoint (with positive values going towards the right or top endpoint).
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>max</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
The maximum data value for the axis --- i.e., the data value corresponding to the
right (for horizontal axes) or top (for vertical axes) endpoint of the axis.
If the axis is a "number" type axis, this value is a number.  If it is a "datetime" type
axis, the value is a datetime in the format YYYYMMDDHHmmss.
</para>
<para>
Alternatively "max" value may be the keyword "auto", which indicates that the maximum
data value for the axis should be computed from the given data.  This only works
for data sources where the entire data set is available at the outset --- it does not
swork for web-service based data sources.
</para>
<para>
The default value for the "max" attribute is "auto".
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>maxoffset</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
A number which determines the point on the axis that will be associated with the
<sgmltag>max</sgmltag> value. <sgmltag>maxoffset</sgmltag> defaults to 0, which means
that the <sgmltag>max</sgmltag> value is associated with the right or top endpoint
of the axis.  If <sgmltag>maxoffset</sgmltag> is not 0, then the <sgmltag>max</sgmltag>
will be associated with a point on the axis that is that many pixels away from
the right or top endpoint (with positive values going towards the left or bottom endpoint).
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>
<xref linkend="figHorizontalAxis"/> and <xref linkend="figVerticalAxis"/>
show how these attribute values determine the way that each kind of axis is displayed
relative to the plot area.  Note that the position of each axis is relative to an edge
of the plot area, but all or part of the axis may lie outside the plot area (in the padding
box).  In particular, a negative <sgmltag>position</sgmltag> value represents a distance
away from the plot area (into the padding box), and 
negative
<sgmltag>pregap</sgmltag>
and
<sgmltag>postgap</sgmltag>
values cause the ends of the axis to extend into the padding box.
</para>

<figure id="figHorizontalAxis">
<title>Horizontal Axis Specifications</title>
<graphic fileref="images/HorizontalAxis.png"/>
</figure>


<figure id="figVerticalAxis">
<title>Vertical Axis Specifications</title>
<graphic fileref="images/VerticalAxis.png"/>
</figure>


<para>
In addition to the above attributes, the <sgmltag>horizontalaxis</sgmltag>
and <sgmltag>verticalaxis</sgmltag> elements may contain the following
subelements:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>title</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
  <para>
The text of this element is used as a title for the axis; it is positioned and oriented according
to the values of the
<sgmltag>position</sgmltag>,
<sgmltag>anchor</sgmltag>, and
<sgmltag>angle</sgmltag>
attributes described in <xref linkend="Positioning"/>.  The 
title is positioned relative to the the center of the axis; the "position" is a pixel offset from this point.
(The "base" point mentioned in <xref linkend="Positioning"/>

The default anchor point depends on the choice and position of the axis. For a horizontal axis,
the default anchor point is "0 1" if the axis is positioned at the bottom of the graph
(positionbase="bottom"), or "0 -1" if the axis is positioned at the top of the graph (positionbase="top").
For a vertical axis, 
the title's default anchor point is "1 0" if the axis is positioned to the left of the graph
(positionbase="left"), or "-1 0" if the axis is positioned to the right of the graph (positionbase="right").
The default angle is always 0.  The default title position also depends on the axis, and has
been chosen to look reasonable in most common situations; see the source file Config.as if you want
to know exactly what the default position values are.
  </para>

  <para>
  If there
  is no <sgmltag>title</sgmltag> element, the axis's title defaults to its
  <sgmltag>id</sgmltag>.  To prevent a title from being drawn at all, use
  an empty <sgmltag>title</sgmltag> tag ("<sgmltag>&lt;title/&gt;</sgmltag>").
  </para>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<!-- *************************************************************** -->

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>labels</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
  <para>
  The <sgmltag>labels</sgmltag> element specifies how multigraph will draw
tick marks along the axis, and text labels for the tick marks.  It has two possible forms,
depending on whether it has a "spacing" attribute.  In the first case, when it does
have a "spacing" attribute, it takes the following attributes:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>format</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
		A string describing the format to be used for tick labels.
The syntax for this string depends on the type of the axis.  For 'number' type
axes, it should be a C-style "printf" format string, such as '%1d', which is
the default.  For 'datetime' type axes, it should be a string containing some combination
of the following special format characters, each of which should be preceeded by a '%':
	  </para>

<para>
<table border="1" cellpadding="2" cellspacing="1">
<thead>
<tr><td>Character</td><td>Expansion</td></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>Y</td><td>four digit year</td></tr>
<tr><td>y</td><td>two digit year</td></tr>
<tr><td>d</td><td>day of month without leading zero</td></tr>
<tr><td>D</td><td>2-digit day of month with leading zero</td></tr>
<tr><td>h</td><td>hour of day, 12 hour clock</td></tr>
<tr><td>H</td><td>hour of day, 24 hour clock</td></tr>
<tr><td>i</td><td>minutes</td></tr>
<tr><td>m</td><td>month number without leading zero</td></tr>
<tr><td>M</td><td>2-digit month number with leading zero</td></tr>
<tr><td>N</td><td>month name, spelled out</td></tr>
<tr><td>n</td><td>month name, 3 letter abbreviation</td></tr>
<tr><td>p</td><td>AM or PM</td></tr>
<tr><td>p</td><td>am or pm</td></tr>
<tr><td>s</td><td>seconds</td></tr>
<tr><td>W</td><td>weekday name, spelled out</td></tr>
<tr><td>w</td><td>weekday name, 3-letter abbreviation</td></tr>
<tr><td>L</td><td>newline</td></tr>
<tr><td>%</td><td>%</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
	</para>

<para>
Any characters in the format string that are not preceeded by a '%' are
included verbatim in the formatted result.
</para>



	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>start</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>	
A data value indicating where tick marks should be aligned on
the axis.  The location of axis tick marks is determined by the
combination of this "start" value and a "spacing" value; multigraph
will draw tick marks (and labels for the tick marks) at locations T +
n*S, where T is the "start" value, S is the "spacing" value, for each
integer n such that T + n*S is visible in the graph's padding area.
The default "start" value is 0.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>spacing</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
A list of values, separated by spaces, giving the possible spacings to be used
between tick marks on the axis.  These numbers should be sorted in decreasing order.
Multigraph will attempt to choose the densest tick spacing possible from amoung
these choices that results in labels that do not overlap.
The default value for the "spacing" attribute is "10000 5000 2000 1000 500 200 100 50 20 10 5 2 1 0.1 0.01 0.001".
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>angle</sgmltag></term></varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>position</sgmltag></term></varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>anchor</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
These determine the location and orientation of each tick mark's label
relative to the location of the tic mark itself.  See
<xref linkend="AxisLabelPositioning"/>
and
<xref linkend="Positioning"/> for further details.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
The second possible form for the
<sgmltag>labels</sgmltag> element accepts all of the above attributes except
the <sgmltag>spacing</sgmltag> attribute;  this form takes a sequence of
<sgmltag>label</sgmltag> subelements instead.  Each label subelement indicates
one possible spacing for axis tick marks, along with other settings to be used
when that spacing is chosen.  Specifically, the <sgmltag>label</sgmltag> subelement
accepts the following attributes:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><sgmltag>format</sgmltag></listitem>
	<listitem><sgmltag>start</sgmltag></listitem>
	<listitem><sgmltag>spacing</sgmltag></listitem>
	<listitem><sgmltag>angle</sgmltag></listitem>
	<listitem><sgmltag>position</sgmltag></listitem>
	<listitem><sgmltag>anchor</sgmltag></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
In the context of a <sgmltag>label</sgmltag> element, these attributes have the same
meaning and form as for the <sgmltag>labels</sgmltag> element, except that the "spacing"
attribute should be a single data value rather than a list of values.  The values specified
by the attributes of a <sgmltag>label</sgmltag> element apply only when the spacing for
that particular element is in effect.  The default value for each of these attributes (except
for the "spacing" attribute, which is required), is whatever value would be in effect
for the containing <sgmltag>labels</sgmltag> element.
  </para>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<!-- *************************************************************** -->

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>grid</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
  <para>
  The presence of this element causes Multigraph to draw grid lines
  perpendicular to this axis, at the location of each tick mark.  The
  <sgmltag>grid</sgmltag> element takes one optional attribute:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>color</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  A hexadecimal number giving the color to be used for the grid lines.  The default
	  is "0xeeeeee", which is very light gray.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
    If a <sgmltag>horizontalaxis</sgmltag>
    or <sgmltag>verticalaxis</sgmltag> element does not contain a
    <sgmltag>grid</sgmltag> subelement, Multigraph does not
    draw grid lines along that axis.  Note that
    the <sgmltag>grid</sgmltag> element only affects the drawing of
    grid lines associated with the axis it appears in.  If you want
    both horizontal and vertical grid lines, be sure to include
    a <sgmltag>grid</sgmltag> element in both
    the <sgmltag>horizontalaxis</sgmltag>
    and <sgmltag>verticalaxis</sgmltag> sections of the &mugl; file.
  </para>


</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>pan</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
  <para>
  This element can be used to configure the type of panning that multigraph
  allows the user to do for this axis.  It accepts the following attributes:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>allowed</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  One of the words "yes" or "no"; default is "yes".
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>min</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  The minimum data value to ever be displayed for this axis; panning is never
      allowed to go below this number.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>max</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  The maximum data value to ever be displayed for this axis; panning is never
      allowed to go above this number.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>


</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<!-- *************************************************************** -->

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>zoom</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
  <para>
  This element can be used to configure the type of zooming that multigraph
  allows the user to do for this axis.  It accepts the following attributes:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>allowed</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  One of the words "yes" or "no"; default is "yes".
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>in</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  The maximum factor by which zooming "in" is allowed, compared to the initial
range of the axis before the user has done any zooming.  Should be a number, or the keyword "none".  Default: "none".
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>out</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  The maximum factor by which zooming "out" is allowed, compared to the initial
range of the axis before the user has done any zooming.  Should be a number, or the keyword "none".  Default: "none".
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>anchor</sgmltag></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
A data value that indicates a location on the axis about which zooming should be centered.  Should be
either a data value, or the keyword "none".  If it is "none", then zooming is centered about 
the location of the mouse cursor when the user first presses the mouse button to begin dragging.
The default is "none".
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
  </variablelist>


</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<!-- *************************************************************** -->

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>binding</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
  <para>
  This element can be used to "bind" two or more axes together with a linear mapping,
so that interactive
panning and/or zooming causes them to move together.  It is typically used to connect
axes that represent the same vertical scale with different units, such as celsius and
Fahrenheit temperature.  It can also be used to connect axes in different graphs that
represent the same scale (for example, the horizontal time axis).
It requires the following three attributes:
  </para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>id</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
The <sgmltag>id</sgmltag> attribute should be a name that identifies the binding.  It can
be any string, and all axes having <sgmltag>binding</sgmltag> elements with the same
<sgmltag>id</sgmltag> value will be connected to each other.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>min</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
A "minimum" value for the binding. Axes bound together in a binding will be connected
in such a way that their "min" values correspond to each other.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>max</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
A "maximum" value for the binding. Axes bound together in a binding will be connected
in such a way that their "max" values correspond to each other.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>


<para>
The  <sgmltag>min</sgmltag> and <sgmltag>max</sgmltag> attributes can be any two
data values on the axis that determine the linear relationship between an axis
and other axes in the same binding.  They do not need to correspond to the axis's
own min and max values, and in general they will not.
</para>

<para>
For example, to bind a celsius
temperature axis to a Fahrenheit temperature axis, you could use the binding
</para>

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<binding id="tempbinding" min="0" max="100"/>
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
on the celsius axis, and
</para>

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<binding id="tempbinding" min="32" max="212"/>
]]>
</programlisting>

<para>
on the Fahrenheit axis.
</para>


</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<!-- *************************************************************** -->

</variablelist>

</section>
