<section id="GeneralStructure">

<title>General Structure</title>

<para>
"&Mugl;" files are the way that you specify to multigraph what data should be
plotted, how it should be plotted, and any other settings that determine the way
the graph looks. &Mugl; (pronounced "muggle") is short for "Multigraph XML", and
is a type of XML file.  Each &mugl; file should
begin with the standard <computeroutput><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0"?>]]></computeroutput>
declaration, followed by the <computeroutput><![CDATA[<mugl>]]></computeroutput> tag.
The general structure of a &mugl; file is shown in <xref linkend="exGeneralStructure"/>.
</para>

<para>
<example id="exGeneralStructure" width="40">
<title>General Structure of a &Mugl; File</title>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<mugl>
  <window .../>
  <plotarea .../>
  <horizontalaxis .../>
  <verticalaxis .../>
  <plot ...>
    ...
  </plot>
  <data ...>
    ...
  </data>
</mugl>
]]>
</programlisting>
</example>
</para>

<para>
The <sgmltag>window</sgmltag> element gives the size of the graph, the size of the border
to be drawn around it, and the margin amounts inside the border.  There can be at most
one <sgmltag>window</sgmltag> element; if it is omitted, multigraph chooses default values
for the border and margins, and relies on the window size given in the Multigraph.Graph
constructor.
</para>

<para>
The <sgmltag>plotarea</sgmltag> element indicates the region inside
the graph window where the data will be plotted.  There can be at most
one <sgmltag>plotarea</sgmltag> element; if it is omitted, multigraph
chooses a reasonable default.
</para>

<para>
The <sgmltag>horizontalaxis</sgmltag> and
<sgmltag>verticalaxis</sgmltag> elements give properties related to
the display and function of the graph's axes.  There can be at most
one <sgmltag>horizontalaxis</sgmltag> element, but any number of
<sgmltag>verticalaxis</sgmltag> elements are allowed.
</para>

<para>
The <sgmltag>plot</sgmltag> element indicates properties of the data plot
itself, such as style, color, which data variables to plot, and which
axes to plot them against.  There can be any number of <sgmltag>plot</sgmltag>
elements.
</para>

<para>
The <sgmltag>data</sgmltag> element gives the data to be plotted, either
by providing the data in a <sgmltag>data</sgmltag> subelement, or by giving
the location of a file or web service from which the data can be read.
</para>

<para>
The following sections describe these elements in more detail.
</para>

</section>
