<chapter id="HTMLFiles">

<title>Creating Multigraph Web Pages</title>

<para>
The first part of any web page containing
a multigraph graph is the HTML file for the web page.
As described in <xref linkend="QuickStart"/>, the HTML file should
load the javascript file "Multigraph.js".  This should
be done in a <sgmltag>script</sgmltag> tag in the <sgmltag>head</sgmltag>
part of the page.
</para>

<para>
There are two other things that need to happen in the HTML file.  The first
is to create a <sgmltag>div</sgmltag> element somewhere in the page, and assign
some value to its
<sgmltag>id</sgmltag> attribute.  This <sgmltag>div</sgmltag> is where
multigraph will draw the graph, and it can be anywhere in the HTML page.
The second is to write a line of the form
</para>

<programlisting>
new Multigraph(DIV_ID, MUGL_FILE, [WIDTH,HEIGHT]);
</programlisting>

<para>
where DIV_ID is the value that you chose for the <sgmltag>div</sgmltag>
containing the graph, MUGL_FILE is the name of the a &mugl; file
describing the graph, and WIDTH and HEIGHT are the width and height
that you want (in pixels) for the graph.  Typically this line should go
in the page body's <sgmltag>onload</sgmltag> attribute, so that it is called
only once, when the page is initially loaded.
</para>

<para>
A web page may include more than one Multigraph graph.  Just create
a separate <sgmltag>div</sgmltag> for each graph, each with its own
unique <sgmltag>id</sgmltag>, write separate
calls to the Multigraph constructor for each one, and create
separate &mugl; files for each one.  If your page contains
more than one graph, you may want to put these Multigraph constructor
calls into a function, and then call that function in the 
page body's <sgmltag>onload</sgmltag> attribute, in order to keep
the <sgmltag>onload</sgmltag> value simple.
</para>

<para>
To view your graph, just load the HTML page into a supported browser
(Firefox or Safari).  When you publish the page to a web server, put your
graph's &mugl; file(s) in the same folder or directory on
the server where you put the HTML file. (Unless your HTML file refers
to it with a relative path, in which case you should put it in the
correct relative location.)
</para>

</chapter>
