<section id="PlotArea">
<title>The Plot Area</title>
<para>
The <sgmltag>plotarea</sgmltag> element 
indicates a rectangular region inside the graph window where the data will be
plotted.  This region is used as another clipping rectangle --- all data plots
shown in the graph are clipped to this rectangle.
Things other than data plots that multigraph draws, such as axes, labels,
titles, legends, etc., can appear outside (or inside) the plotarea (these
other things are clipped to the padding box as described in
<xref linkend="BordersAndMargins"/>.
</para>

<para>
It accepts the following attributes, which represent offsets relative
to the padding area defined in the <sgmltag>window</sgmltag> element:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>marginbottom</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Offset from the bottom side. Default: 30.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>marginleft</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Offset from the left side. Default: 30.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>margintop</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Offset from the top side. Default: 10.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>marginright</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Offset from the right side. Default: 30.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>
The padding box and plotarea both serve as clipping regions for
various parts of the picture that multigraph draws.  The relationship
between these two regions, and how they relate to the window (the
"div" region in the containing HTML page), is shown in <xref
linkend="figPlotarea"/>; in this figure the padding box is white and
the plotarea is green.  The padding box serves as the clipping region
for everything that multigraph draws, other than the border.  This
includes axes, labels, legends, etc.  The plotarea, which is inside
the padding box, is the clipping region for data plots.
</para>

<figure id="figPlotarea">
<title>Plotarea</title>
<graphic fileref="images/MarginBorderPlotarea.png"/>
</figure>

<para>
There can be at most one <sgmltag>plotarea</sgmltag> element in a &mugl; file.  If it
is absent, all attributes assume their default values.
</para>

</section>
